part 3 chapter 3.
There are three stages in your reintegration said O'Brien There is
learning, there is understanding, and there is acceptance.
It is time for you to enter upon the second stage.'
As always, Winston was lying flat on his back.
But of late his bonds were looser.
They still held him to the bed, but he could move his knees a little and could
turn his head from side to side and raise his arms from the elbow.
The dial, also, had grown to be less of a terror. He could evade its pangs if he
was quick-witted enough: it was chiefly when he showed stupidity
that her brand pulled the lever.
Sometimes they got through a whole session without use of the dial.
He could not remember how many sessions there had been. The whole process seemed
to stretch out over a long, indefinite time— —weeks, possibly— —and the intervals
between the sessions might sometimes have been days, sometimes only an hour or two.
'As you lie there,' said a brand you have often wondered— —you have even asked me—
—why the Ministry of Love should expend so much time and trouble on you.
And when you are free you have puzzled by what was essentially the same
question. You could grasp the mechanics of the society you lived in, but not its
underlying motives.
Do you remember writing in your diary, "I understand how: I do not understand why"?
It was when you thought about "why" that you doubted your own sanity. You have
read the book, Goldstein's book, or parts of it, at least. Did it tell you anything
that you did not know already?'
'You have read it?' said Winston.
'I wrote it.
That is to say, I collaborated in writing it. No book is produced individually, as you know.'
'Is it true, what it says?'
'As description, yes. The program it sets forth is nonsense. The secret
accumulation of knowledge— —a gradual spread of enlightenment— —ultimately a
proletarian rebellion— —the overthrow of the Party. You foresaw yourself that that
was what it would say.
It is all nonsense. The proletarians will never revolt, not in a thousand years or a million.
They cannot. I do not have to tell you the reason: you know it already.
If you have ever cherished any dreams of violent insurrection, you must abandon them.
There is no way in which the Party can be overthrown. The rule of the Party is forever
Make that the starting point of your thoughts.'
He came closer to the bed forever he repeated.
'And now let us get back to the question of "how" and "why".
You understand well enough how the Party maintains itself in power.
Now tell me why we cling to power. What is our motive?
Why should we want power? Go on, speak,' he added as Winston remained silent.
Nevertheless Winston did not speak for another moment or two
the feeling of weariness had overwhelmed him. The faint, mad gleam of enthusiasm
had come back into O'Brien's face.
He knew in advance what O'Brien would say. That the Party did not seek power
for its own ends, but only for the good of the majority.
That it sought power because men in the mass were frail cowardly creatures who
could not endure liberty or face the truth, and must be ruled over and
systematically deceived by others who are stronger than themselves. That the
choice for mankind lay between freedom and happiness, and that, for the great
bulk of mankind, happiness was better.
That the Party was the eternal guardian of the week a dedicated sect doing evil
that good might come, sacrificing its own happiness to that of others.
The terrible thing, thought Winston, the terrible thing was that when O'Brien
said this he would believe it.
You could see it in his face a brand new everything. A thousand times better than
Winston he knew what the world was really like, in what degradation the mass of human
beings lived and by what lies and the barbarities the Party kept them there.
He had understood it all, weighed it all, and it made no difference: all was
justified by the ultimate purpose.
What can you do, thought Winston, against the lunatic who is more intelligent than
yourself, who gives your arguments a fair hearing and then simply persists in his lunacy?
'You were ruling over us for our own good,' he said feebly. 'You believe that human
beings are not fitted to govern themselves, and therefore———' He started and
almost cried out. A pang of pain had shot through his body. O'Brien had pushed the
lever of the dial up to 35.
That was stupid, Winston, stupid!' he said.
'You should know better than to say a thing like that.'
He pulled the lever back and continued: 'Now I will tell you the answer to my
question. It is this.
The Party seeks power entirely for its own sake. We are not interested in the
good of others; we are interested solely in power.
Not wealth or luxury or long life or happiness: only power, pure power.
What pure power means you will understand presently.
We are different from all the oligarchies of the past, in that we know what we are doing.
All the others, even those who resembled ourselves, were cowards and hypocrites.
The German Nazis and the Russian Communists came very close to us in
their methods, but they never had the courage to recognize their own motives.
They pretended, perhaps they even believed, that they had seized power
unwillingly and for a limited time, and that just around the corner they lay a
paradise where human beings would be free and equal.
We are not like that. We know that no one ever ceases power with the intention of
relinquishing it.
Power is not a means, it is an end.
One does not establish a dictatorship in order to safeguard a revolution; one
makes the revolution in order to establish the dictatorship.
The object of persecution is persecution.
The object of torture is torture. The object of power is power.
Now do you begin to understand me?'
Winston was struck, as he had been struck before, by the tiredness of O'Brien's
face. It was strong and fleshy and brutal, it was full of intelligence and a sort
of controlled passion before which he felt himself helpless;
but it was tired. There were pouches under the eyes, the skin sagged from the cheekbones.
O'Brien leaned over him, deliberately bringing the worn face nearer.
'You are thinking,' he said, 'that my face is old and tired. You were thinking that I
talk of power, and yet I am not even able to prevent the decay of my own body.
Can you not understand, Winston, that the individual is only a cell?
The weariness of the cell is the Vigor of the organism. Do you die when you cut
your fingernails?'
He turned away from the bed and began strolling up and down again, one hand in his pocket.
'We are the priests of power,' he said. 'God is power. But at present power is only a
word so far as you are concerned. It is time for you to gather some idea of what
power means.
The first thing you must realize is that power is collective.
The individual only has power in so far as he ceases to be an individual.
You know the Party slogan: "Freedom is Slavery." Has it ever occurred to you that
it is reversible?
Slavery is freedom.
Alone— —free— —the human being is always defeated. It must be so, because every
human being is doomed to die, which is the greatest of all failures.
But if he can make complete, utter submission, if he can escape from his
identity, if he can merge himself in the Party so that he is the Party, then he is
all-powerful and immortal.
The second thing for you to realize is that power is power of human beings. Over
the body— —but, above all, over the mind.
Power over matter— —external reality, as you would call it— —is not important.
Already our control over matter is absolute.'
For a moment Winston ignored the dial. He made a violent effort to raise himself
into a sitting position, and merely succeeded in wrenching his body painfully.
'But how can you control matter?' he burst out. 'You don't even control the climate
or the law of gravity.
And there are disease, pain, death———' O'Brien silenced him by a movement of
his hand. 'We control matter because we control the mind. Reality is inside the
skull. You will learn by degrees, Winston.
There is nothing that we could not do.
Invisibility, levitation— —anything. I could float off this floor like a soap bubble
if I wish to.
I do not wish to, because the Party does not wish it.
You must get rid of those 19th century ideas about the laws of Nature. We make
the laws of Nature.'
'But you do not you're not even masters of this planet. What about Eurasia and
East Asia You have not conquered them yet.'
'Unimportant. We shall conquer them when it suits us. And if we did not, what
difference would it make? We can shut them out of existence. Oceania is the world.'
'But the world itself is only a speck of dust. And man is tiny— —helpless! How long
has he been in existence? For millions of years the earth was uninhabited.'
'Nonsense. The earth is as old as we are, no older. How could it be older? Nothing
exists except through human consciousness.'
'But the rocks are full of the bones of extinct animals— —mammoths and mastodons
and enormous reptiles which lived here long before man was ever heard of.'
'Have you ever seen those bones, Winston?
Of course not 19th century biologists invented them. Before man there was nothing.
After man, if he could come to an end, there would be nothing. Outside man there is nothing.'
'But the whole universe is outside us.
Look at the stars! Some of them are a million light years away.
They are out of our reach forever What are the stars?' said O'Brien
indifferently. 'They are bits of fire a few kilometers away. We could reach them
if we wanted to.
Or we could blot them out. The earth is the center of the universe. The sun and
the stars go around it.'
Winston made another convulsive movement.
This time he did not say anything.
O'Brien continued as though answering a spoken objection:
'For certain purposes, of course, that is not true. When we navigate to the ocean,
or when we predict an eclipse, we often find it convenient to assume that the
earth goes round to the sun and that the stars are millions upon millions of kilometers away.
But what of it? Do you suppose it is beyond us to produce a dual system of astronomy?
The stars can be near or distant, according as we need them.
Do you suppose our mathematicians are unequal to that? Have you forgotten doublethink?'
Winston shrank back upon the bed.
Whatever he said, the swift answer crushed him like a bludgeon.
And yet he knew, he knew, that he was in the right.
The belief that nothing exists outside your own mind— —surely there must be some way of
demonstrating that it was false?
Had it not been exposed long ago as a fallacy?
There was even a name for it, which he had forgotten.
A faint smile twitched to the corners of her Brian's mouth as he looked down at him.
'I told you, Winston,' he said, 'that metaphysics is not your strong point.
The word you are trying to think of is solipsism.
But you're mistaken. This is not solipsism. Collective solipsism, if you
like. But that is a different thing: in fact, the opposite thing.
All this is a digression,' he added in a different tone. 'The real power, the power
we have to fight for night and today is not power over things, but over men.'
He paused, and for a moment assumed again his heir of a schoolmaster questioning a
promising pupil: 'How does one man assert his power over another, Winston?'
Winston thought.
'By making him suffer,' he said.
'Exactly. By making him suffer.
Obedience is not enough.
Unless he is suffering, how can you be sure that he is obeying your will and
not his own?
Power is in inflicting pain and humiliation.
Power is in tearing human minds to pieces and putting them together again
in new shapes of your own choosing.
Do you begin to see, then, what kind of world we are creating? It is the exact
opposite of the stupid hedonistic Utopias that the old reformers imagined.
A world of fear into treachery and a torment, a world of trampling and being
trampled upon, a world which will grow not less but more merciless as it refines itself.
Progress in our world will be progressed towards more pain.
The old civilizations claimed that they were founded on love or justice.
Ours is founded upon hatred. In our world there will be no emotions except fear,
rage, triumph and self-abasement.
Everything else we shall destroy— —everything.
Already we are breaking down the habits of thought which have survived from
before the Revolution. We have cut the links between child and parent, and
between man and man, and between man and woman.
No one dares trust a wife or a child or a friend any longer.
But in the future there will be no wives and no friends. Children will be taken
from their mothers at birth, as one takes eggs from a hen. The sex instinct will be
eradicated. Procreation will be an annual formality like the renewal of a ration card.
We shall abolish the orgasm. Our neurologists are at work upon it now.
There will be no loyalty, except loyalty towards the Party. There will be no love,
except the love of Big Brother. There will be no laughter, except the laugh of
triumph over a defeated enemy.
There will be no art, no literature, no science. When we are omnipotent we shall
have no more need of science.
There will be no distinction between beauty and ugliness. There will be no
curiosity, no enjoyment of the process of life.
All competing pleasures will be destroyed.
But always— —do not forget this, Winston— —always there will be the intoxication of
power, constantly increasing and constantly growing subtler.
Always, at every moment, there will be the thrill of victory, the sensation of
trampling on an enemy who was helpless.
If you want a picture of the future, imagine a boot stamping on a human face forever
He paused as though he expected Winston to speak.
Winston had tried to shrink back into the surface of the bed again.
He could not say anything. His heart seemed to be frozen.
O'Brien went on: 'And remember that it is forever The face
will always be there to be stamped upon.
The heretic, the enemy of society, will always be there, so that he can be
defeated and humiliated over again.
Everything that you have undergone since you have been in our hands— —all that will
continue, and worse.
The espionage that betrayals, the arrests, the tortures, the executions, the
disappearances will never cease. It will be a world of terror as much as a world
of triumph. The more the Party is powerful, the less it will be tolerant:
the weaker the opposition, the tighter the despotism.
Goldstein and his heresies will live forever Every day, at every moment, they
will be defeated, discredited, ridiculed and spat upon— —and yet they will always
survive. This drama that I have played out with you during seven years will be
played out over and over again, generation after generation, always in subtler forms.
Always we shall have the heretic here at our mercy, screaming with pain, broken up,
contemptible— and in the end utterly penitent, saved from himself, crawling to our feet of his
own accord.
That is the world that we are preparing, Winston. A world of victory after victory,
triumph after triumph after triumph: an endless pressing, pressing, pressing upon
the nerve of power.
You are beginning, I can see, to realize what the world will be like.
But in the end you will do more than understand it. You will accept it, welcome
it, become part of it.'
Winston had recovered himself sufficiently to speak.
'You can't!' he said weekly What do you mean by that remark, Winston?'
'You could not create such a world as you have just described. It is a dream.
It is impossible.'
'Why?'
'It is impossible to found a civilization on fear and hatred and cruelty. It would
never endure.'
'Why not?'
'It would have no vitality. It would disintegrate. It would commit suicide.'
'Nonsense. You are under the impression that hatred is more exhausting than love.
Why should it be? And if it were, what difference would that make?
Suppose that we choose to wear ourselves out faster. Suppose that we quicken the
tempo of human life till men are sent out at 30.
Still what difference would it make? Can you not understand that the death of the
individual is not death? The Party is immortal.'
As usual, the voice had battered Winston into helplessness. Moreover he was
injured that if he persisted in his disagreement O'Brien would twist the dial again.
And yet he could not keep silence Feebly, without arguments, with nothing to
support him except his inarticulate horror of what O'Brien had said, he returned to the attack.
'I don't know— —I don't care. Somehow you will fail. Something will defeat you. Life
will defeat you.'
'We control life, Winston, at all its levels.
You are imagining that there is something called human nature which will
be outraged by what we do and will turn against us.
But we create human nature. Men are infinitely malleable.
Or perhaps you have returned to your old idea that the proletarians or the slaves
will arise and overthrow us.
Put it out of your mind. They are helpless, like the animals. Humanity is
the Party. The others are outside— —irrelevant.'
'I don't care. In the end they will beat you. Sooner or later they will see you
for what you are, and then they will tear you to pieces.'
'Do you see any evidence that that is happening? Or any reason why it should?'
'No.
I believe it.
I know that you will fail. There is something in the universe— —I don't know,
some Spirits some principle— —that you will never overcome.'
'Do you believe in God, Winston?'
'No.'
'Then what is it, this principle that will defeat us?'
'I don't know. The spirit of Man.'
'And do you consider yourself a man?'
'Yes.'
'If you are a man, Winston, you are the last man. Your kind is extinct; we are the
inheritors. Do you understand that you are alone?
You are outside history, you are non-existent His manner changed and he said more
harshly: 'And you consider yourself morally superior to us, with our lies and our cruelty?'
'Yes, I consider myself superior.'
O'Brien did not speak. Two other voices were speaking.
After a moment Winston recognized one of them as his own. It was a soundtrack of
the conversation he had had with O'Brien, on the night when he had enrolled
himself in the Brotherhood. He heard himself promising to lie, to steal, to
forge, to murder, to encourage drug taking and prostitution, to disseminate venereal
diseases, to throw vitriol in a child's face her Brian made a small impatient gesture,
as though to say that the demonstration was hardly worth making.
Then he turned a switch and the voices stopped.
'Get up from that bed,' he said.
The bonds had loosened to themselves.
Winston lowered himself to the floor and stood up unsteadily.
'You are the last man,' said O'Brien. 'You are the guardian of the human spirit. You
shall see yourself as you are.
Take off your clothes.'
Winston undid the bit of string that held his overalls together.
The zip fastener had long since been wrenched out of them.
He could not remember whether at any time since his arrest he had taken off
all his clothes at one time.
Beneath the overalls his body was looped with filthy yellowish rags, just
recognizable as the remnants of under clothes As he slid them to the ground he saw
that there was a three-sided mirror at the far end of the room.
He approached it, then stopped short.
An involuntary cry had broken out of him.
'Go on,' said O'Brien. 'Stand between the wings of the mirror. You shall see the
side view as well.'
He had stopped because he was frightened.
A bowed Gray colored skeleton-like thing was coming towards him.
Its actual appearance was frightening, and not merely the fact that he knew it to be himself.
He moved closer to the glass. The creature's face seemed to be protruded,
because of its bent carriage.
A forlorn, jailbird's face with a knobby forward running back into a bald scalp, a
crooked nose and battered looking cheekbones above which his eyes were fierce and watchful.
The cheeks were seamed, the mouth had a drawn in look.
Certainly it was his own face, but it seemed to him that it had changed more
than he had changed inside.
The emotions it's registered would be different from the ones he felt.
He had gone partially bald. For the first moment he had thought that he had gone
gray as well, but it was only the scalp that was gray Except for his hands and a
circle of his face, his body was gray all over with ancient, ingrained dirt.
Here and there under the dirt there were the red scars of wounds, and near the
ankle the varicus also was an inflamed mess with flakes of skin peeling off it.
But the truly frightening thing was the emaciation of his body.
The barrel of the ribs was as narrow as that of a skeleton: the legs had shrunk
so that the knees were thicker than the thighs. He saw now what O'Brien had meant
about seeing the side view.
The curvature of the spine was astonishing. The thin shoulders were
hunched forward so as to make a cavity of the chest, the scraggy neck seemed to
be bending double under the weight of the skull and I guess he would have said that it
was the body of a man of sixty, suffering from some malignant disease.
'You have thought sometimes,' said a brand that my face— —the face of a member of the
Inner Party— —looks old and worn.
What do you think of your own face?'
He seized Winston's children spun him around so that he was facing him.
'Look at the condition you were in!' he said. 'Look at this filthy grime all over
your body. Look at the dirt between your toes. Look at that disgusting running sore on your leg.
Do you know that you stink like a goat?
Probably you have ceased to notice it.
Look at your emaciation. Do you see?
I can make my thumb and forefinger meat around your bicep. I could snap your neck
like a carrot.
Do you know that you have lost 25 kilograms since you have been in our
hands? Even your hair is coming out in handfuls. Look!' He plucked at Winston's
head and brought away a tuft of hair.
'Open your mouth 9 10 11 teeth left. How
many had you when you came to us? And the few you have left are dropping out of
your head. Look here!'
He seized one of Winston's remaining front teeth between his powerful thumb
and forefinger. A tinge of pain shot through Winston's jaw
Brown had wrenched the loose tooth out by the roots. He tossed it across the cell.
'You were rotting away,' he said; 'you were falling to pieces. What are you? A bag of
filth. Now turn around and look into that mirror again. Do you see that thing
facing you? That is the last man. If you are human, that is humanity.
Now put your clothes on again.'
Winston began to dress himself with slow stiff movements.
Until now he had not seemed to notice how thin and weak he was.
Only one thought stirred in his mind: that he must have been in this place
longer than he had imagined.
Then suddenly as he fixed the miserable rags around himself a feeling of pity
for his ruined body overcame him.
Before he knew what he was doing he had collapsed onto a small stool that stood
beside the bed and burst into tears.
He was aware of his ugliness, his gracelessness, a bundle of bones in
filthy under clothes sitting weeping in the harsh white light:
but he could not stop himself. O'Brien laid a hand on his shoulder, almost kindly.
'It will not last forever he said. 'You can escape from it whenever you choose.
Everything depends on yourself.'
'You did it!' sobbed Winston. 'You reduced me to this state.'
'No, Winston, you reduced yourself to it.
This is what you accepted when you set yourself up against the Party.
It was all contained in that first act.
Nothing has happened that you did not foresee.'
He paused, and then went on: 'We have beaten you, Winston. We have
broken you up. You have seen what your body is like. Your mind is in the same
state. I do not think that there can be much pride left in you. You have been
kicked and flogged and insulted, you have screamed with pain, you have rolled on
the floor in your own blood and vomit.
You have whimpered for mercy, you have betrayed everybody and everything. Can
you think of a single degradation that has not happened to you?'
Winston had stopped weeping, though the tears were still losing out of his eyes.
He looked up at O'Brien.
'I have not betrayed Julia,' he said.
O'Brien looked down at him thoughtfully.
'No,' he said, 'no; that is perfectly true.
You have not betrayed Julia.'
The peculiar reverence for O'Brien, which nothing seemed able to destroy, flooded
Winston's heart again.
How intelligent, he thought, how intelligent!
Never did O'Brien fail to understand what was said to him.
Anyone else on earth would have answered promptly that he had to betrayed Julia.
For what was there that they had not screwed out of him under that torture?
He had told them everything he knew about her, her habits, her character, her
past life; he had confessed in the most trivial detail everything that had
happened at their meetings, all that he had said to her and she to him, their
black market meals, their adulteries, their vague plottings against the Party— —everything.
And yet, in the sense in which he intended the word, he had not betrayed her.
He had not stopped loving her; his feelings towards her had remained the same
Brian had seen what he meant without the need for explanation.
'Tell me,' he said, 'how soon will they shoot me?'
'It might be a long time,' said O'Brien. 'You are a difficult case. But don't give up
hope. Everyone is cured sooner or later.
In the end we shall shoot you